for UX and customer discovery. Uh UX is
something that uh I discovered um a
while back, so more than 10 years back
as being the base for uh everything that
I do. So I have the user in mind all of
the time. And so did the designer of
this table when um they built uh this
table for giraffes because otherwise it
would hurt their neck to drink at a
cocktail bar that would be uh much
lower. So this is actually UX and it is
not only based for software AI or
interaction but also uh on physical um
on physical objects and for customer
discovery.
We will talk a lot about interviews,
about discussing with users. This whole
deck and whole discussion is about the
fact that you need to get out of the
building and discuss with users. And I'm
going to teach you how to do that right
because also you can discuss uh with
users say that you did but uh if you're
not doing it right then it's for
nothing. [snorts] So um you can see here
uh an example uh of a founder that goes
and talks to uh his parents and uh
you'll find out that this is not the way
uh in which you should do it because
your parents will always uh love your
ideas because guess what they're your
parents and they need to love you and
your ideas uh the same. So we start with
this. If you look it up all over why do
startups fail, you'll find this 20 top
reasons why they fail. But the first and
foremost and usually this is what
happens in any industry is the inability
to understand market and customer
demand. So basically creating something
that is for nothing and for no one
because no one will then buy it. Why
does this happen? It happens because
usually we create tech and stuff based
on what we think it is needed. This is
what we think and what actually happens
in the real world uh can be two very
different things. And before we talk to
the market, we talk to customers and we
actually validate our ideas in a way in
which it works. We don't just give them
money to tell us that our idea is good
just so that we feel fulfilled.
Then this is why startups fail.
Basically they move on with the product.
Maybe they also raise some money or put
their own money in it and at the end no
one actually pays for it and they need
to lose everything that they've invested
just because they didn't validate from
the very beginning that the thing they
are building will actually sell. And why
do I say that it is important to sell?
Now um you are here in innovation labs
because of course everyone will ask you
about your business model about how
you're selling you also learn about
business models here you can also learn
from everywhere but um what it is
important for a business because this is
why it's called a business it's not a
hobby it's not a sidekick it's not an
NGO it's not a social project it's a
business you need to sell you need to
make money because otherwise it's it is
a hobby That is the point of startups.
Either make a lot of money and be uh
profitable or exit and sell and be very
very profitable for the founders or
people that have a stake in the company.
And also in the area of investors,
everyone wants to get money out of it,
of course. The second of course is
spending money and running out of cash.
you might think that um I don't know
100,000 uh euros is a lot of money or 1
million is a lot of money but when you
are in a startup that becomes a runaway.
So you need to make sure that you have
money in that runaway so that you can
support your company with all of the
growth that is coming because when
someone invests in your company they
expect for you to grow. So you need to
invest the money super smartly and
usually startups fail because they run
out of money and guess what even though
maybe they have clients in their
pipeline they will need to close because
they cannot pay for their servers or
something like that.
Third is the inability to form and
maintain a diverse team. Maybe this is
something that changed a bit now due to
AI because the diverse team um is
everyone. So everyone should be diverse
at the moment. So you shouldn't just
wear one hat because now you can learn
everything from the beginning and do
everything. But uh the inability to form
uh a team uh is something that everyone
actually not only in startups but in
everything that you do also in NOS's so
that say innovation labs has a team
behind it is difficult to do leading and
leadership in the team. So you might
also think about that UX and product uh
are two things that should work in
parallel. Um product has a lot of UX in
it as well because product uh is
something that uh stays between and
these are the three most important
topics that go into product is UX. So
user experience in general, user flows,
how the user actually um interacts with
the product and feels it. The tech
because product managers uh usually
interact a lot with the um not only
developers but in general with how the
product is built and the business like
sales, pre-sales, customer support and
so on. and understanding the needs of
the business and the market and how the
product is positioned there. Okay, so
all of this part so product is an
umbrella role but you also need UX and
we're going to talk first about UX. Um
and here you can also see a way um other
ways to to look at the tasks of design
and product management so that you also
know um the roles that you're going to
need to cover in your product. What they
both have in common and when where we
are getting is that um they can both
assume that the customers will know how
to use it. As I told you, UX is about
how users um experience the product. So
this assumption that customers know how
to use it before testing it, before um
showing it to them, before actually
testing that hypothesis, it might be
wrong because users I won't say users
are stupid because and you shouldn't say
that either because that's not true.
only designs and experiences are stupid
because you've been building them for
users that uh become frustrated when
they use it. So, you should build tools
that are easy to use. And easy to use is
a term that is um used a lot but never
um when it is put on a slide um and you
ask about UX and user experience in
general and user research no one knows
uh how to answer. They just say I made
it easy to use or the AI designed it
easy to use. It is not easy to use until
you put it in the hand of a user and you
look at them and see that they know how
to use it. But what they have in in
common is that they are problem solvers.
So they solve the problem of the users.
And this is why I also like the job of
uh product management in general uh
because there are always problems that
we need to discover from the users
perspective that we solve through our
solutions. UX has a lot of definitions
from different parts uh but um it is
usually um this umbrella term that
describes all of the interactions that
the user has with the product. And why
do I say that it's all of the
interactions all of the factors is
because it's not only that uh I can use
the product is how I perceive it how I
like it. So if we think of products such
as I don't know the Apple ecosystem, you
get used to it because the experience is
moot. It sol it solves some of the
problems that uh you encountered with
other uh platforms maybe that they
solved uh along the way but um you like
something also because of the brand for
example how they uh present themselves
their simplicity their innovation. So UX
is in all of your touch points with uh
the brand. So you need to take care of
this user experience or customer
experience in the future not only in how
they interact with your product but also
how you uh talk about the product.
What's in it for you to look at UX? Um
and I wanted to tell you also something
that I mean in the last years this with
UXUI is still a mis uh a misused term
and it is confused. Um
usually UX is like a joke. If you have
to explain it, it is not that good. So
uh and UI is the what you see are the
beautiful parts. The fact here that you
see the Hines um ketchup bottle on the
left hand side, it is nice. It looks
good. Has the logo and so on. But guess
what? Whenever you as a user of the
ketchup bottle, you want to use it, you
will keep it the other way around.
Therefore, in order to see the brand,
you need to put the label uh in the um
yeah, rotate it, right? And in order to
get also the usability out of it, so to
make it usable, to get the last bit of
ketchup on your pizza, you will need to
make it more appropriate in terms of how
you hold it and also to uh allow the the
users so to have this um feature that
you get all of the ketchup out otherwise
they'll be missing product the product
out of it. A lot of companies are
investing a lot in UX. Um, and this uh
is very important because when you
invest $1 in UX at the beginning, the
return on investment is 100fold.
Uh and how we can look at that the other
way around is that um if you don't
invest that $1, it is possible that you
will lose 100 in the future because if
you haven't tested your uh hypothesis
from the beginning, you haven't tested
your experience, you didn't um allow the
users to interact with your product,
then you will lose $100 in development
money because you will develop it, you
will ship it, it will get to users, they
won't know how to use it. So, they will
never buy again from you and you lose
that money that you could have uh
invested in the beginning and uh won in
the future. So, usually through UX and
thinking about the user experience and
putting the user first, not building
just because it's cool, you will achieve
everything faster, your business goals.
uh you will have a higher return on
investment on every um dollar every now
we're talking dollars or money you
invest time at the moment that means
money as well so let's say an hour of
your time and put this 100fold
um and if a customer is happy from the
beginning from the first time they use
your product it is easy for them to use
it then they will recommend you to
others or they will talk nicely about
you. But if you annoy them, if the
experience is bad, uh if the design is
bad, then uh you will need to do uh
around uh from five to seven good deeds
after so that you rewin that customer.
These are the two sides of uh the brain
in terms of UX and UI. So the UI is
visual design, colors, graphic design,
layouts and typography. and the rest of
it is um the interaction doing
prototypes information architecture user
research and so on. How does uh AI fit
in all of this and how it does not?
Usually in UX and in UI, AI is
inspiration.
It doesn't mean it validates all of the
things that you have there. So um what
you can do uh in UX is to use AI as a
critique master to do critique for flows
and screens. So you should do the flows
and screens and AI should do the
critique because you don't have a
designer to do a critique for you or a
product manager. Um I mean you might
have mentors that can do it but to deep
dive you can do that with uh AI. You can
get inspiration for UI patterns. what I
can tell you about UI patterns because
now um uh why why designers are
important in my experience working on I
don't know I I think I worked on more
than 60 products um as um in a role of a
developer designer uh or product manager
and on countless features I did a lot of
competitive analysis and I looked on a
lot of other solutions also in
innovation labs, I've seen hundreds or
even more uh products or states of a
product. So
even though uh I didn't do it um in a
school because there's no school for
that, I saw a lot of UI patterns for
specific things. So now I do know when
to use what or when to suggest what in a
screen.
But you can use AI to do that and you
can ask about UI patterns. Customer
discovery because we are there now.
Customer discovery in my opinion for you
now uh is very important. What is it? It
actually comes from a book called the
four steps uh to epiphany
uh by Steve Blank uh which came before
Eric Risley startup. If you haven't read
this books or at least one of them, you
should
um reading about it or discussing with
the summary on Chajibet won't replace
you reading this just so so you know and
it will change um the way in which you
perceive this whole subject and how to
build products with AI without AI it
doesn't matter everything that they put
here stands and there are things that
cannot be replaced uh by AI in product
management and that's customer discovery
done right. Uh so again a lot of
startups fail from a lack of market need
um and they do fail um quite fast if
they don't uh especially if they don't
find the money. Um
and why why does it happen? because as a
best practice what you should do when
building a startup and don't feel bad
now if you didn't do this yet because
you can do this now in one week you can
do this with the deliverables that we're
going to ask for you you're going to be
able to do this for your startup
starting tomorrow
usually you discover a market need let's
say you said that you did that you
usually define a hypothesis with both
need and proposed solution so your
pitches, your lean model canvas. That's
a hypothesis.
I know that there's that need or that
problem in the market for whomever and I
do have this solution. This is a
hypothesis. This is not proven until you
discuss with customers and validate it
directly that someone will pay for it in
a way in which it makes sense. Um you
are not validating it. If the market is
big, if someone else did it, blah blah,
it doesn't matter. You need to do it and
you need to validate this through
customer discovery with your startup,
with your idea, with your solution, with
your team. You should complete customer
research. So this is how customer
discovery is done. Usually you do
customer interviews, focus groups,
surveys.
You will see that I will suggest and the
deliverables will be customer
interviews. That's because you don't
you're not able to do focus groups
enough to prove a point like big
companies do. And surveys can be very
leading. That doesn't count as real
customer discovery for a product. So you
really need to discuss face to face with
users. Usually you analyze all the data
and information and you uncover
insights. The insights might be uh very
painful for you because you might
invalidate your hypothesis and you
should be happy if the hypothesis is
invalidated because at least now you can
focus on another hypothesis that might
be validated and you wouldn't have
worked like a year of your life
investing into something that no one uh
will use and usually you need to act on
those insights. So uh you should move on
to delight customers and if you uh
invalidate your hypothesis and that
specific thing that specific solution
that specific feature whatever doesn't
make sense because you need to do this
not only at the beginning of the product
but all of the time when you need to add
something in it then you should move to
something else if it doesn't uh delight
uh users. So how do you define
hypothesis? Usually you define them like
this and uh you will see at the the end
you can do this with AI. It will uh help
you and it will give you examples if you
give it the right context. Um and they
should be not very high level. So you
should deep dive onto the hypothesis. So
of course your big solution and big
problem are the ones from your pitch.
But when you deep dive on what features
you are going to put there, you will uh
see that you need to validate the
tiniest hypothesis. So if you're
building something for the blind, you
need to demonstrate that the blind,
I don't know, want to use that tool in
general. Uh and that they will know how
to use it, that they need it, that they
will pay for it, that they will pay $100
a month or they will pay $10. Those are
all all hypothesis. So everything you
think about at the moment are
hypothesis. So hypothesis are looking
like that. So our proposed solution
solves a problem with the solution
and they are testable. They are clear.
So testable means that you can go in an
interview with a user with a set of
questions that validate or invalidate
your hypothesis and at the end you can
say yes it is definitely validated or
definitely invalidated because if you go
there just to validate it you are lying
to yourself. So and they should be
clear. They should be uh specific
and uh they can be about the product. So
what to put in the product they can be
about the customer like I don't know
blind people need something about the
channel. So I need to do this on web on
mobile only channel I need to do it in a
prompt I don't know uh about pricing how
much it should cost how much they would
pay. So if I give you a very fast
forward example, uh a lot of people
assume that students will pay for
something. Students won't pay for
something. So because they don't have
money, they don't have their own money.
So they won't pay for anything. We also
have the market. So what market you are
uh moving towards.
Um and we also have the competition. So
you assume that the competition is
building something uh because of
something. whatever you need to validate
that uh hypothesis also you can check
feasibility. Um so can we actually do
it? Uh do they want it or uh should we
do it? And you after that after putting
all of this uh hypothesis and counting
them you can put them on this risk risk
assumption matrix because sometimes you
cannot prove all of your hypothesis.
Therefore, maybe you have no evidence
for them and they're quite important.
So, that's one. But even though you
don't have evidence, you mark them here
and you move ahead without having
evidence, but you take the risk in the
future that this might not pay off. If
you have evidence and they're important,
you put them in that area and you mark
them there. And this is quite useful to
know where you are investing everything
because if everything is important and
you have no evidence for it then you
shouldn't do it because then you are
working on something that you have no
evidence uh against and it's um not
worth it. Maybe you will find out that
you need to talk to customers. That's
very important. Maybe you didn't do this
before. Most probably you didn't and it
is hard but you need to do it because
otherwise you are not building you might
not build the right product for them and
you want them to pay for it. So the
benefits you understand your target
customers you'll see also how you do a
persona. Um you test your assumptions so
it's be it's going to be much easier for
you to discuss uh about them and to say
that yes these are validated users need
this. um you can discover how to do your
business model. So you will discover
that if those guys don't pay for it then
the other guys need to pay for it
otherwise I won't have um profit in my
my company. Finding the product market
fit product market fit is uh the holy
grail of startups. In early stage, your
goal is to fine-tune your product based
on the customer discovery that you do so
that uh you increase your chances to
achieve this product market fit. And
yeah, you save time and money. That's
super important. What's the most painful
thing in my opinion when building
products, when being a builder in
technology is building something that
will never be used by anyone. That
sucks. If you invest a lot and a lot of
money without getting anything in return
of course and you are not getting good
feedback from users, no one wants to use
it. Um that is bad. So it will hurt and
it is better uh to invest time in
talking to users, building something
that matters and after and by that
saving your your time investment and
yeah foster customer loyalty. As I said,
customers are happy if you make
something that they want to use and that
they need uh not something that you
would uh that they would hate using.
You will answer this question if they
will buy it or choose to use it, if they
can use it, if you can build it. um if
it works for your business because you
might discover that this is not
something that you can build or want to
build because you might discuss with
users and realize that what they need
you cannot build or you don't want to
build.
Building the right thing for the right
people discover the real problems. What
you might realize when talking to users
is that um you start with uh you'll see
I will tell you how to make your
questions uh but you start with
something trying to validate your
assumptions through open questions and
you might realize that the problem that
you assume that they have it's a very
small problem in a big ecosystem of
other big problems that you are not
solving for them. Therefore, for that
little tiny problem, they won't use your
product even though the problem exists.
So, this is why you need to talk to them
to see how uh you fit in their ecosystem
and discover their real problems and you
might discover that other problems are
um more important and they will pay
money to solve those rather than
something that you started with. You go
there to validate assumptions or to
invalidate them. It's the same. And you
need to fall in love with the problem.
So um you need to find this problem
space where to find a problem to fall in
love with so that you can find the right
solution. Because if you fall in love
with directly with the solution without
validating that there's a problem,
you'll get to uh to issues.
What we recommend you to do is user
interviews.
So questions you ask your users. These
will be uh actual discussions that you
have with users and that's a research
method used during the discovery phase
where the interviewer ask participants
questions about a specific topic and
they show you who they are and what they
do. Not only do you like my product,
because that's not a question you should
ask, but to understand what their life
is. Just to give you an example, if you
are building for construction site
workers, guess what? You'll need to talk
to construction site workers
to see how they work. The best
interviews are 90% listening and only
10% talking and they are not informal.
They shouldn't be informal. They should
be uh written uh down with a guide um
and whatever I will tell you now. So you
need to identify what you would like to
learn. At the beginning you will do
something that we call exploratory
interviews because you're not doing
interviews on a specific specific topic.
At the beginning we you should go to
validate the whole problem space and
deep dive into those users that you
think are your users. You should prepare
a guide and we're going to discuss a bit
about that. You should pilot uh that uh
that guide. Uh and um pilot I mean um
talk to someone in an interview session
that would be more friendly. Um, and at
the beginning you should start easy
build report. What that means is that if
you haven't done interviews until now
with users, you're going to see that you
cannot just go there and uh start asking
you questions and then leave and expect
that everything goes smoothly because uh
human interactions don't look like that.
This sort of interviews should be
recorded. You should have a colleague
that is uh with you to write notes and
you should have the questions written
down. Social cues that I will mention
and maybe these are things that you can
also use moving forward also in
mentoring. You should make eye contact.
Guess what? That is important to make
eye contact. You should nod. So whenever
someone talks to you and you want to
interview them, so you want them to feel
comfortable telling you different things
and answering to your questions because
guess what? People tend to not answer
your questions openly if you are not
friendly.
um you should do this nodding so that
you approve what they say even though
they might not be right but if you nod
um they will get the feeling that you
are listening to them you are paying
attention and you'll agree and they can
move forward so it's a confirmation you
should mirror them mirroring is
something that maybe we do unconsciously
but you should do consciously because in
this sort of interviews maybe in the
first 100 that you do you won't feel
that comfortable doing stuff. Mirroring
is for example, if they drink water, you
drink water because you saw that they
drink water.
If they nod, you nod and so on. So this
sort of mirroring works also maybe in
dating if you do that. So if you think
about it, that's a fun fact to know.
Echoing. What echoing means? It means
when they say something like a sentence,
you repeat the last words of the
sentence. That's quite helpful. People
actually appreciate that because they
see that you paid attention to what they
said or at least that's what they
understand through so that social cue
and approval. You say, "Yes, yes, I
understand. That's great. Sure. Wow.
That's how it works." So that they um
build up on it because you need info.
You need them talking 90% of the time.
You need all of their problems on the
table so that they talk and talk to you
so that you discover more and more about
the problem that you are trying to
solve. How you ensure that an interview
is effective not like this. So if you go
there and uh you tell them you should be
completely honest. Tell us what you
think about the product or tell us what
you think about this problem. Tell us
what you think about your day. But just
so you know, we are losing all of our
nights, all of our weekends, all of our
money, we don't have a salary, we don't
have what to eat, we are struggling.
Please tell us it's a good idea.
Don't do that. You need u reality. You
don't need uh lies from um uh this sort
of interviews. So you need to you need
them to be real rather than to tell you
what you like. And this is why usually
AI um that validates you and your ideas
it's very tricky to use in this sort of
uh situations in regards to customer
discovery. Other tips that you might use
and these are uh stuff that um I found
um during my my interviews. You should
uh interview one person at a time uh and
you should pay attention fully to that
person. It can last for I don't know uh
30 minutes is uh quite uh low as a
target but you should do 45 minutes an
hour with the person especially at the
beginning so that you have time to do
everything that you you want. You should
always prepare. So this is very
important. You shouldn't go in an
interview with a uh potential user
because we are not selling anything.
They're not customers. Okay? So we don't
want to sell them anything. We should
prepare. We should have our questions.
We should at least seem prepared and
respectful of their time. Okay? This is
the way in which you start. You should
take notes and do follow-ups afterwards.
So you shouldn't go there and uh after
that you should just call your
co-founder and and say, "Yeah,
everything was nice. They answered yes
to everything." No, you should have
questions with answers. You should do a
recording. You should have a transcript.
You should put that transcript maybe
somewhere in an AI do um evaluation and
a follow-up and summary for the whole
team. Okay? So, you can do this much
easier now. In the past, we did the
transcript by hand. We listened to it
and did the transcript by hand and did
the summary, you know, by hand. So, now
you have the power of doing all of this
with AI. So please do that and enjoy the
experience of the interview fully and do
as many interviews as you can because
afterwards you can use all of this data
and cluster it and play around with it
um and discuss it with the whole team uh
in a much easier uh fashion. You should
try to kill your idea. So this is the
best way in which you can go right now
um to do customer discovery. So you
should push it to the max. If it doesn't
die in this customer interviews
that means it you should move forward
with it. And just so you know mentors
and everyone in innovation labs are not
um evil. uh they're not asking you
questions uh because they hate you in
some way and they don't trust you with
your idea. They're actually trying to
kill it because they're trying to do
well by you and kill it or actually tell
you how it can be killed or what you can
validate or invalidate early on because
mentors see patterns. They've seen some
things. They have their questions in
their mind. So everything that they say,
everything that they ask you, you should
use as things to validate, as hypothesis
to validate. Even though you don't know
how to answer, uh you need to go there
and validate all of those things. Okay?
You should ask open-ended questions and
ask for clarifications.
You should never ever ask a question
that can be answered by yes or no.
So that's why do you like this product
is a wrong question because it can be
only yes because no one will tell you
no. You should ask how does your workday
go? How do you do that specific flow? Uh
what applications you have on your
computer and how do you use them? What
apps do you pay for every month? Do you
play any games? Um does your do do your
children use any uh any apps? Do you
blah blah. Okay. So you are validating a
problem space uh and you are asking
questions that are open so that people
can open up in front of you and tell you
the whole context.
You shouldn't lead them on. So you
shouldn't ask leading questions. You'll
notice quite fast when your questions
are leading because they will answer
what you expect them to. the right
questions when they are not leading you
will never know what they might answer
and they have the opportunity to tell
you something that will hurt you. So
that's why you shouldn't lead them
towards your um wanted answer. You
shouldn't sell. So in customer
interviews, in customer discovery in
general, the point is not selling
is to validate assumptions and don't
pitch it because it's it's not the
point. You are validating the problem so
that you build that specific solution.
You are not pitching it. Uh there
selling and pitching is done by other
people not uh who you are in customer
discovery. You need to wear other hats.
Everyone lies. That is unfortunate but
true. You need to dig deeper. Uh in time
you will um realize uh how this works
and you will feel when people are not
telling you everything. But usually the
first uh things that they say uh is um
things that make them feel good or make
them um escape you faster.
So in general you need to make it um be
a discussion so that they tell you like
they tell a friend but about their job.
You should choose a neutral and quiet
environment. No one can talk when they
have noises around and it should be
neutral in the sense of it shouldn't be
an interrogation
and customers do not know everything. So
you shouldn't expect that they know what
you should build. they know about their
lives, their their uh ways of working,
their uh day in life. Uh so they they
don't know what you should build for
them to solve their problems. Only you
can define that because if they would
know, they would build it for
themselves. You should maintain a
beginner's mindset. So you shouldn't be
arrogant or seem like you know better.
Even though maybe in some contexts with
users
um they might be from another industry,
they might not know tech.
So, but you should maintain a beginner's
mindset with their industry with what
they're doing because they if they are
open and they you don't seem like the
smarters in the room and you listen to
them uh then they will tell you exactly
how their uh industry works, how their
work works. You should create a
conversation, not an interrogation. You
shouldn't ask them what they want from
you because guess what? again they don't
know because if they would have known
they would have built it themselves and
you should spend times with users often
this should be I don't know every week
you should spend time with users you
should understand them and avoid yes or
no questions and don't look for approval
look for insights so this is how we call
things that we get out of this whole uh
interview process we look for insights.
Okay? And those insights we analyze and
we transform into uh hypothesis
validation or invalidation. You should
uh look at the mount test. It there's a
book but there are also videos that you
can search for and you should look at
this so that you know um better how to
uh do customer interviews. I cannot
explain it better than this. It's like
the best way to to get your info. How AI
fits. You can use AI to validate or
generate interview questions. Um, you
should make sure that you are following
all of the rules, but you can simulate
also interview scenarios, especially at
the beginning. You can discover what you
can expect in interview scenarios more
than I can tell you, but it is
unexpected. You might meet people that
are super talkative that will tell you
everything and you'll be so amazed about
what you discovered and you might meet
people that
don't say anything. Uh you can structure
the interview notes. Of course you can
use many tools for for that. But yeah uh
and you can extract patterns from
multiple interviews and see what's
common. But guess what? Your mind
already will do that. So if you are in
all those interviews you will already
have the patterns the insights and so on
because talking to users um when done
right with the right right questions um
it's amazing how many things uh you you
find out. So with AI you prepare and
analyze you don't replace the talking to
users. You shouldn't validate your idea
with AI because not AI will use your
product but people users
uh and you shouldn't decide what users
need without talking to users and
validating a need with users because uh
AI is kind of fiction. Um a prompt you
should yeah be a UX researcher um or you
can also be a product manager in this uh
situation. [snorts] You can generate
open-ended questions. You can put in all
of the information I put around this or
generate another prompt that is much
longer that would give you better uh
results.
Um and uh yeah here like focus on
behavior shouldn't do leading questions.
You can tell them to use uh you can tell
uh the egg to use the mom tests book and
insights and yeah you should not ask for
opinions. I just put here uh some things
that are uh important to mention. Next
is experiments and why you should do
them. Uh experiments is a concept that
exists in all sorts of uh of products.
It involves testing different ideas and
approaches to actually identify what's
best um and as benefits. Um it's the
same benefit. It's like this is a method
uh from uh customer discovery. You have
the reduced risk of implementing the
wrong thing. Uh you validate
assumptions. So it's a method before
actually doing a heavy investment into
that specific feature. You have
datadriven insights. That's very uh very
good. And usually you enhance the user
experience because this is what we're
talking about. Experiments can also be
like sort of AB testing let's say
[snorts] and it prevents this solution
first thinking. So it encourages problem
validation rather than uh moving into to
solutions. You usually define an
objective and the hypothesis that you
are trying to test. Maybe you I mean you
looked into it in the hackathon as well.
you but you designed the experiment.
The experiment can be something super
easy uh or it can be something more
complex more thought through. It depends
and you of course you collect and
analyze the data and you iterate and
learn. So here on the left hand side you
see a small example of um a hypothesis
that also includes the experiment that
you are trying to to do. So if we
actually reduce the number of buttons
which is a variable we
make only one button rather than two or
whatever then we'll get more
registrations. So we are aiming to get
more registration which is the variable
two by reducing the number of buttons
and we make an experiment. We reduce the
number of buttons and see if the
registration's number uh goes up. That's
the same as if we make the button red or
green and see uh if we have more clicks
on it. So this is a small experiment.
What other concepts and types we have in
experiments? We have this hypothesis
driven approach. So every experiment
starts with testable hypothesis. As we
said before we have the independent and
depend dependent variables which are
what you change versus what you measure.
So the registration versus the number of
buttons. Uh the minimum viable
experiment
um we talk a lot about minimum viable
product but the minimum viable
experiment is the smallest text test
that you can do in order to get
actionable data and you need to aim for
that because you don't have so much
money as to invest in a big experiment
that would validate all of the data and
you should avoid bias. bias uh can get
involved also in the interviews that you
do because also interviews are sort of
experiments. Um
uh you should be very aware of that
because bias can get um very tricky. We
have customer discovery interviews where
you validate the problem solution fit
for different things. We have landing
page tests for example. You put uh a
button register here will notice you
when we are up. You check demand. You
have this wizard of oz or concierge
MVPs. Um what these mean and these can
be used a lot uh in terms of uh what we
have now with um AI. This wizard of wars
or concier MVPs uh are um clickable
prototypes or not so clickable. So
staged prototypes
when um you as the person doing the
interview the testing um the user says I
would go that way or I will use this
prompt or I will do that and you tell
them what happens next and usually you
do this scenarios um yeah by guiding the
user rather than he or she actually
testing a solution. This is also um this
is useful when uh you test um what they
expect to get as a result in terms of uh
when you're building something from an
AI. Uh you do AB testings. That's also
an experiment where you have multiple
versions, not just AB but CD EF. Um and
you compare versions for conversion
impact. You can have fake door tests.
So, you can have buttons throughout your
app that go different places that don't
exist. So, you have a feature that edits
something and um yeah, it doesn't work,
but you count it in in an analytics tool
and you say, "Okay, 100 people actually
clicked on it, so I might as well
implement it." And smoke tests. Smoke
tests are usually ads that go to a
signup page. These are quite uh used so
that you see that uh the demand exists.
These are some experiment cards. Um I
truly advise you to always document your
work. If you do it and don't document it
is not as valuable because you won't be
able to go back to it and show it to
other people and and so on. So even
though it's all in your head, it's not.
So uh you need this documentation that
can be now filled much easier and and so
on. So please uh document what you are
doing,
how it fits usually to accelerate your
work. um you cannot use it as evidence
because if you know how AI works um it's
not evidence of real um user behavior.
Um but you can um experiment with
different experiment types so that it
gives you ideas.
Uh you don't need to look a lot for
ideas that are easy and so on. It can
give you tons of it. You can define the
hypothesis that you can test. You can
generate, I don't know, landing page
copy or do a ton of landing pages or ads
or stuff. And you can brainstorm a lot
on test variations and what you should
focus and so on for that m um minimum
viable experiment. You shouldn't use AI
to decide if your idea works. So skip
the experiments. Do the experiments with
AI. you shouldn't skip running it ever.
So people are still um people companies
are heavily doing this anyhow and it
doesn't replace real user behavior. Jobs
to be done is another tool that uh you
need to to know of. It's an approach to
developing products by looking at the
jobs of the customer and the processes
that would lead uh that customers to
hire a product to do the job. So um why
I um tell you about this is that we
usually look at how the current state in
the users's life uh is how things are.
Um what's the outcome? The outcome is
them using our product. Love it. But
what is the progress towards there?
Because if the progress is super hard
then they won't make the change and uh
use your product. So you need to take
care [snorts] uh of this jobs to be done
and know about them because uh usually
the process of them actually getting to
use your product is more important uh
and more lengthy and it's a cost that
they don't want to pay. So maybe that is
why they won't use your product even
though yes it would be useful. You
should build first your problem
statements. So I kept saying problem
space and so on. Uh usually this is how
you start with a problem and if you
cannot emphasize your problem uh in a
problem statement template it's a
problem. Who uh who has the problem?
What is the problem? When does it occur
and why? So when we look at the why, we
look at how big the problem is for the
user because there are some small some
small problems that I would never pay to
get solved. So
you need to address the problems that
are most painful. When if it happens
once a year, I won't pay for it. Maybe I
need to do it only once a year. So
therefore, why pay for it? and what and
who you already know. Going to the last
subject because we talked about UX,
customer discovery, experiments and now
we talk about user persona. That's your
target customer and it is a fictional
representation of a type of customer.
It's a fictional representation. It's
not gigel
from Vaslu that I know it's the friend
of someone. No, it's gigel. a fictional
representation like an actor, okay, that
represents everyone that has specific
characteristics
and they answer the question, who are we
building this product for?
So, uh, and it's at the heart of the
design design process. Usually we um
invest a lot into um finding the right
persona for [clears throat] a specific
product or usually we find first the
persona its problem and then drill down
to who will buy. What are the relevant
questions? What age group do they
represent? What's the group of people
that actually does those actions that we
are targeting with our solutions? and
they have no restrictions between each
other because when we look for example
in a product we might have different
user personas. So let's say we are
building a tool for children. Um
children are um don't have money so they
won't pay for that product. They also
don't have um they have their maybe
their own device but they're not
managing it. Therefore, we also have the
parents. So, we'll have at least two
personas. If we're targeting kids uh
under 10 years old versus kids over 10
years old, again, two different
personas.
If we're targeting uh um an app for kids
that also make sense um educationally.
So, we also have teachers. Let's say
another persona comes in. Each of these
persona completes a set of action in the
platform
and they have restrictions between each
other. Right? So someone controls the
actions of the other. So you need to
build all of these personas and discuss
with all of them.
What is their current approach? How do
they solve this problem that you tell me
that they are having? How are they
trying to solve it? if they are solving
it and how much does it cost them
really? Why do they have this existing
work model? Why don't they have
something simpler? Why didn't they go in
a direction to solve that problem? Maybe
they don't know. Maybe didn't didn't
try. Why didn't they try? They don't
have money. They don't have tools. They
don't want to install that. You need to
explore all of that when you go into
customer uh discovery because otherwise
you'll just assume that you are solving
a problem but maybe they don't want to
solve it or they don't know how to solve
it or they tried and it didn't work. You
need to know if they did that. What are
their common needs, their pains, their
goals? What do they actually want? Not
from your product but in general what
are their needs and what are uh what is
their purpose? Why do you want why do
they want something? Because when you
want, for example, an application for
your um
uh your child uh you want that
you don't want specifically an app that
would cover something for for them. You
are investing in a bigger purpose,
right? So you need to understand that
you need to understand the whole uh
problem space and where you fit in their
uh overall purpose. These are some
examples of two different personas for a
shopping app. Uh it's Maria and Florine
very different personas specifically on
technology needs uh financial motivation
and so on. So when Florine buys uh from
um and orders from a delivery a food
delivery app uh they um are looking at
uh price ranges. It's split they split
their delivery costs with their friends.
Um maybe uh he he's looking for um yeah
optimizing costs in general and have
this nutritional information because
he's into nutrition and sports and
stuff. Um looking at promotions is
something that is very useful for him.
Um whereas for Maria
um maybe she doesn't have uh this
experience with technology so much. She
especially uses uh only her phone maybe
um she cannot compare with other shops
with other products. Uh she doesn't want
to have her products selected by other
people. Um so they don't have a stock
for local products or she would want
that or to filter for that. So here you
can see two different personas. If you
are trying to sell a product to both of
them, you need to cater to their needs
because if you only cater for one, they
will only use it uh only they will use
it and Maria will not be your customer
and the other way uh around. Okay, kind
reminder. You really need users. So, you
need to talk to users and guess what?
They won't knock at your door so that
they find you and they tell you
everything about their lives and what
they they need. So, um you should not
wait. You should reach out to possible
customers and start doing your customer
interviews.